Mr. Men? Here. Mr. Arroyo? Here. Mr. Cleese? Here. Ms. Gregg? Here. Ms. Diaz? Here. Mr. Hirsch? Here.
And President Becay? Council President Becay is excused this evening a few friendly reminders please note this meeting is being live streamed and recorded today's committee meeting does not have a scheduled public comment period but councillors may invite public comment after each item on their agenda if you are making a public comment please do so at the microphone state your name and address for the meeting record also please be sure to silence any cell phones and devices one note item 6 resolution 64 would not be presented during the community planning committee this evening and has been stricken from the agenda I'll hear a motion for the approval of the August 11th 2025 committee meeting minutes motion to approve motion to hear second Second. Second. Motion and a second.
Mr. Harris? Mr. Mudd?
Aye.
Mr. Arroyo? Aye. Mr. Gilles? Aye. Ms. Gregg? Aye.
Ms. Diaz? Aye. Mr. Hirsch?
Aye. We'll kick it over to the personnel committee. Councillor Clicks? Thank you, Vice President. The personnel committee has two items on the agenda for tonight. The first item is the nomination of Keisha Finney for appointment to the public art advisory board. so miss finney has been working has been serving on the board for some time and her term has expired and she is willing to be reappointed as an alternate alternate member of the board and i'll open up for any comments questions from console from other members of the committee
council colleagues thank you i would just like to say that uh miss finney has been a great public advocate for art here in the city and i look forward to seeing her reappointment
Thank you for your comment, Councillor.
Councillor Kleeks. Just also want to add, many of you know Keisha through her work as an artist here in Lancaster City. And as someone that serves on that board, I think it's really important that we have local artists on that board. So I'm really glad that we're reappointing Keisha.
Thank you, Councillor, for your comments. Any other comments or questions from Council as a whole, from the public? Hearing none, I'll make a motion to move this nomination to our next Council meeting. second all in favor aye thank you and the next item is the nomination of Stephen Campbell for reappointment to the sewer appeals board so mr. so there isn't much to say about this reappointment so I just want to thank mr. Campbell for willing to continue to serve on the board I'll open up for questions and comments from other members of the committee and console from the public I'll make a motion to move this termination to our next console meeting second all in favor aye thank you that concludes the personal
committee vice president Thank You councillor colleagues we'll move to the Finance Committee this evening we have one item on our agenda administration bill number six 2025 which is authorizing the issuance of a general obligation note with that I'll invite director Campbell to introduce the bill
good evening good evening so tonight we're introducing an ordinance for the general obligation an ordinance of a general obligation note this note is for interim bank financing for the 42 inch water transmission main line that we've discussed on several other occasions over the last year or so and the project has also been included in our capital plan for a few years and is included in the capital budget that we've been presenting since june and you will see the first reading of that ordinance for the capital budget on september 9th because this project is for the water main this debt will be financed through the water enterprise fund and will not affect the general fund in march you may remember we reviewed as we reviewed the 2025 bond financing we discussed that we would be returning to you later this year for financing for this project so this is us returning to you for this project and as you may recall we included this debt in our projections when we showed the principal and interest costs for the bond on the graphs that you received for that bond because we knew that this project was coming so as a reminder this project will ultimately long term be financed through penvest penvest requires that the project be shovel ready before they will loan funds so all of the design engineering permitting must be completed and the work needs to be ready to start before PenVest will award the loan because of the timing of some of the grant funds that we were awarded for this project and because of some of the current uncertainties for timing of procurement of equipment and materials we would like to get orders out for the materials for this project before PenVest will award the funds for the long term funds so that the grant funds are assured of being used and so the project can start as soon as possible when we get the loan funds from penvest if you recall we initially thought that we would include some of this funding for the materials in the bond financing however penvest will not refinance permanent or bond financing so this is an interim banknote financing and this will allow us to move all of the costs eventually into the penvest loan as they do allow interim financing to be included in long term debt this will keep interest costs down very significantly for us as penvest interest is lower than bond financing and it will make the in the interim financing well worth the savings and interest expense and daryl will talk a little bit more about that as well the interim financing is also structured as like a line of credit so we will only draw down and therefore only pay interest on what we actually need to use so i'll now turn it over to daryl to provide more context
uh good uh uh thank you tina um for that introduction and great to be before you again as indicated uh we talked about this earlier this year i know time flies here we are in september already um i put before you a narrative and uh some one financing schedule and one graph so hopefully we can walk right through that and make sure you have an understanding of what we're doing and why we're doing it uh and and tina touched on a lot of this but uh clearly you're moving forward with the water transmission line project um i'm not the engineer in public works but as i understand it that's gonna uh you know provide resiliency and redundancy to the sole water main that was put in put in place and put in the ground in uh 1955 uh 1955 and uh you know with that it's certainly reaching towards the end of its useful life um so the total cost of the project is estimated at 41 million dollars um as tina indicated the permanent financing for the project is expected to be secured by pennsylvania infrastructure investment authority most of you know it as penvest and the city and its project engineer in the process moving that application forward um and uh again as tina indicated uh you know due to the expected time required until the the city is prepared to make that application and more importantly, actually receive the funding. You know, it behooves you to to secure this interim financing in the amount of about $32 million. So that you'll can pre order and purchase the primary materials being the pipe hydrants, and fittings, etc. By having those available when you actually go forward and bid the construction phase of the project, you should absolutely certainly expected that you will, you know, one, be able to proceed in a more timely manner to move the project forward. And maybe more importantly, from a cost saving stand standpoint, is you should get better bids for the construction phase because the contract for no, when they get when they put the bid in and get awarded, they're going to get to work right away as opposed to, you know, starting to work six months later with, you know, some unknowns. So I really think that's this is clear this whole plan was really obviously put together by uh department of public works and your engineers etc so we're just helping move that forward and facilitate it with this interim financing um right now we're the the city's at its uh sort of immediate or crucial requirement i don't get too technical but you may have heard this before uh in order to move forward with securing the interim financing that we're going to do you get what's called a letter of no prejudice uh from penvest what that means uh in plain vanilla talk is that by having that letter of no prejudice you can now incur the costs and potentially even pay the cost um before you actually get the penvest financing so it's kind of no prejudice that you can include those costs and roll it into the financing so at the end of the day the interim financing will be paid off and rolled into the lower industry pen best financing, again, as Tina said, instead of including them in the 2025 bonds, so a lot of interest costs saved by rolling the primary costs being the materials into the pen best loan and not doing it under what would be more conventional financing. So with that, page two is really putting together the schedule, not the project schedule intertwined with the financing schedule. I'm going to stress this is tentative. I think you all understand we try to remain fluid and nimble. And I also stress that this is a sequencing schedule. You know, I'm going to put dates here, but understand that if you know kind of an early event slips, that means the whole schedule is going to slip. So I think it also just gives you a framework of how these all intertwine and move together. So of course, we're giving you the presentation this evening in mid-september we expect to get the letter of no prejudice again that critical document from pen vest and with that letter of no prejudice in hand we would actually we Concord would actually move forward with the interim financing request for proposals to be sent to the banks and then we hold the City Council at the City Council meeting we would hold the first reading that may or may not be on September 9th that may be on september 23rd again i think we're going to stay need to stay a little bit nimble there and then moving forward on this timeline then in mid-october we would get the bank proposals obviously we review them and make a recommendation as to the best proposal and at the city council meeting in october whether it be october 14th or october 28th have the second reading actually accepting a proposal and critical critical we must have the letter of no prejudice in hand before you award financing if not we risk having this project not being eligible for penvis so obviously we're very cautious of that and wouldn't bring it to you beforehand um then as the current schedule uh on october 29th uh the city plans do actually submit the uh permanent financing application to penvest um then we would close on the interim financing in mid october uh mid november having that inner financing in place that assures you you have funds in the amount of the 32 million dollars to actually place that order again you wouldn't want to place order for 30 million dollars of of uh equipment or materials that you don't have financing in place for um and then so you can and that project lead time for those project materials is four to six months so that's really the lead time that you're gaining uh in your schedule by doing the interim financing then with the penvis application towards the end of october the next pen best meeting for the award of financing is in january of 2026 again moving forward in the timeline in february february slash march the project materials would be received and you would be moving forward with the construction bid phase uh for forbidden awards so again then you'd be ready to move forward with the actual actual project commencement then in april and may of 2026 you'd have your legislative process or your ordinance process for the permanent penvest financing uh project construction would begin we would expect to close on the penvest permanent financing and when you get the penvest permanent financing in hand and in place you would actually pay off the interim financing for the for the materials portion the project is expected to be completed in april of 2027. we are going to let the interim financing uh have an extra year of its maturity again trying to be cautious um we all know projects can get delayed and also the there's a secondary purpose of the interim financing not only to bridge the materials acquisition but you can also use that interim financing for like cash flow for the project because if ever the reimbursements that come from penvest would not be quite timely you want to have the interim line of credit is serving a dual purpose it's the materials phase and it's also the potential delay that you might have from penvest because they work on a reimbursement basis the most we can have is a year we're allowed to have the interim financing be one year after the estimated completion date so that should be sufficient for you well tina touched on the top of page three the interim financing is on a drawdown basis or a line of credit again minimize on the interest expense the interim financing will also provide an amount to pay the interest on the interim financing during the project phase and that's to avoid the budgetary impact um you know you're gonna have to go through the puc process etc to be able to raise water rates outside the city so the plan would be to have the the interim financing also be available to pay the interest to the extent you want to do so not a requirement to do so but it's available to do so uh should that uh be necessary within the budget uh the next bullet i i uh mentioned that the internet financing will mature in june of 28 to be that additional one year provide the project cash flow um moving forward on page four um kind of like a sources and uses here of the of the interim financing again two critical points provide the funds to order and purchase the materials and to provide the bridge loan or cash flow loan during the project phase so the total cost of the financing will be 32 million dollars um that's providing really four components uh the 30 million dollars for the project materials to be purchased uh estimated capitalized interest or interest on the interim financing of about 900 000 the financing costs and about a million dollar reserve again for that project cash flow need remember you won't draw on that you won't use that unless you absolutely need it but it's there in case you need it so that's how we arrived at a interim financing note of 32 million dollars the next schedule is really presented as a not to exceed amount it's kind of like i have to show you that but no way do we expect the interest expense to be that great because again at the drawdown and the prepayments and lastly on page five again a graph similar that you have seen before and actually showed you as a looking forward uh back in back in march we were doing 2025 bonds so the red bars here are the existing water fund debt service and the blue lines are the expected water fund debt service after what would be the 41 million dollar pen invest financing and how you and how you step into it so overall water fund debt service will go from about 15.1 million uh next year uh up to about 18.5 million uh beginning of 2020. um questions or um so let
me entertain those can i just add quickly too i don't don't think anybody from dpw is here from public works but i did just want to say the timeline might seem a bit aggressive and we did talk to them about that quite a bit so it sounds like we will have three different contractors doing the work because we are able to get all the materials together where it's easier to be able to do that so it'll kind of be work going on simultaneously which will increase the speed of it but one of the main reasons for that is and I won't get into all of the details but to try to to ensure that we can get this in our PUC rate case as quickly as possible just because we know it's such a big project and a large portion of it is for out for outside of the city as well as some inside so just wanted to comment on that schedule and if there's questions about specific questions about the the schedule or the project itself we can have Public Works comment on those at a
later date for the presentation um a couple questions uh with this being short-term financing is the rate variable or is this a fixed rate i see here there's a five percent yeah that's an
estimate um actually when we do our request proposals we will ask for both variable rates uh and fixed rates probably probably your preference would be to have a fixed rate um but with the short-term nature we're going to see what we get you know kind of like bid it out or ask for both and do an analysis and figure out what's more beneficial if we get kind of a very aggressive or favorable variable rate um and we'll certainly get a cap rate you know just look at what the variable is in the cap versus what the fixed rate is that we get so thank you and my
second question is uh with the short-term financing being 32 million is the remaining nine million estimated the estimated construction costs any uh further questions from the committee
not not the committee but i just want to thank um tina and the department of public works and with the assist from concord i think one of the things that's very momentous about this and i just don't want it to get lost in in the mix is the point that tina was making about the aggressive schedule in the past we have not been we have been borrowing money to do the design and then and then do the construction and we have had large sums of money that have been sitting not being utilized in in an aggressive time fashion and that is a habit that we have been trying to work ourselves out of I think for the last eight years because when you borrow money you should be spending it very quickly within three to four years you that money should be in the ground and then that should be coming back this is going to be really aggressive with a borrowing here we are at the end of almost you know the end of 2025 2028 this project is complete so two years in these are the kinds of benchmarks that council should be asking for in the future to really understand if the capital projects are indeed ready and that we're going to spend the money in the time frame that we need to and so i really applaud tina director campbell the directors campbell steve and tina for really leading off on this work and the kind of planning that went into the capital planning effort overall is allowing us to do this and council should also be really monitoring the frequency in which we are going to penvest for rate case increases because as tina mentioned this is a very this is a once in a generation um uh improvement that is being made and while it's 40 million dollars for this phase it's a lot more than that when you add all
three phases together thank you for that context mayor sirachi any questions or comments from the finance committee any questions or comments from council as a whole councillor hirsch thank you um
and this might not be the question for you this might actually be more of a question for public works but i just see that there's an estimated four to six month delivery for the materials how solid do we feel about that given i mean i don't know what if anything is being sourced from overseas but with the trade situation kind of being volatile i'm just curious if the city
has any thoughts on that i think that is probably more of a question for public works i will say i i asked a few different ways if they feel confident with that four to six months and they were they were feeling pretty confident about it so i think they can probably give more details but
thank you councillor hirsch any additional questions or comments from full council
thank you mr vice president um and thank you for the presentation this was very helpful um my only question is and you may have answered this when we do have the rfps from the banks is that going to be something that council will approve or is that something that the administration
will unilaterally take care of um so typically we receive those rfps back and then bring the proposed rfp from the administration to council um you would see that with the second reading of the ordinance so you would see the full the full amount then am i saying that am i stating
that correctly yeah the ordinance itself will will accept uh the proposal that is being recommended
thank you and that concludes my questions mr vice president thank you councillor med any additional questions or comments from council any from the public great thank you both for the presentation this evening um i will move to or i will motion to move bill number six to the september 23rd meeting for first reading second motion in the second all those in favor aye aye that concludes the finance committee uh we'll move on to community planning councillor craig thank you council vice
um we have five items on the agenda this evening first being the review of the historical commission reveal the historical commission recommendation for demolition of a garage at
53 north water street good evening mayor good evening council this um resolution is a recommendation from the historical commission to approve a demolition of a two-bay one-story freestanding cement block garage behind where the bread peddler is at 53 on 53 north water street it is it was built in the 1940s and they did receive zoning approval on july 23rd and the historical commission is recommended recommended approval at their meeting on august the 7th for demolition of this and it will remain as a surface parking lot cut and dried are there any questions
from the committee councilor just um is the parking lot short term or have they mentioned any long-term use potentially for that space there it's a pretty small space in fact the
reason why they want to demolish it is because they feel like it's not safe to try and pull two cars in there so i believe it's going to remain as a surface parking lot as far as i
understand thank you are there any questions from council as a whole just a comment i did look at it
on google maps and yeah it's it's going to be like a space or two at most so that's what hurts
um well then that will do that um i'll make a motion to move this forward to september 9th second all those in favor all right thank you um the next item we have on the agenda is administration resolution 61 authorizing an application for local shares and we have several applications for local shares so i think what we're going to do i'm sorry council
okay i think we have resolution number 60 on the agenda next 60 oh thank you very much
okay administration resolution number 60. i skipped right over top of it my apologies amending a projection easement granted to hacker arcade condominium association and i'm glad you're
here so take it away thank you the original resolution was passed by city council on may 14 2024 and if you recall it granted an easement so that balconies for the condominium condominiums can hang over north water street and west grant street the original easement agreement incorrectly listed the required height of the balconies as 15 feet above the street but the amended easement agreement is intended to correct the minimum height to 13 feet and six inches which is in compliance with the city ordinance is current and currently in place and that is the only change to
the easement agreement this evening thank you i have no questions about that um are there any questions from the committee questions from council as a whole or comments uh just a quick
question um if it were up to me i would probably you know if i could wave a magic wand me personally i would take uh traffic off of the west grant street portion by market but i do know that some box trucks do go through there every now and then are we OK with the height in light of that. I don't know if it would be an issue or not but it's just a question I have.
That is a very good question. This came through the Department of Public Works and the right of way engineers so I will have to get back ask them and get back with you on that.
They probably yeah they probably only overhang like the sidewalk so I'm sure it's fine.
but how far is the bump out i guess that's the question yeah thank you councillor hirsch that
was a great question um i'll make a motion to move um administration resolution 60 to full council on the 9th second all those in favor aye aye thank you now we will move on to administration resolution 61 authorizing an application to local shares account program by the lancaster city lancaster public library and then there are several local shares accounts that we will review thank you director campbell
thank you um so before we get into the resolutions i wanted to just give a brief overview of the link of the local shares account or lsa grant program i'll refer to it as lsa this evening um this is a pens this is a pennsylvania statewide program that's funded through the commonwealth financing authority and it distributes state gaming revenue so it's now the fourth year of this statewide program there was there were some individual counties that did it previously but this is the fourth year for the statewide program so grants can be awarded from 25 000 up to a million dollars through this program and there's no match requirement which makes it very popular for community benefit organizations in the community the grantee must be a governmental agency of some sort so we do get many requests from community benefit organizations to apply for this program and then we serve as the grantee and they serve as the sub grantee more than one grant can be awarded to the governmental agency or the municipality and previous years we have received multiple grants for the community through this program so just to give you a summary in the first three years we have made 35 applications for LSA grants on behalf of community benefit organizations and and a couple of city projects as well 12 of those applications were awarded at least partially and it totaled six million nine hundred and twenty three thousand dollars in funds to the to the community which is great um and then the remaining 23 grants 12 were denied but 11 are still pending from last year the awards have not been made yet for those applications so the lsa funds can be used for acquisitions of property purchase of equipment or construction projects either new or remodeling and you'll see a range of all of those projects in these requests because this is a state grant and we are the grantee we must have a resolution from council allowing us to apply for each individual grant these resolutions commit the city to applying for the grant but it does not guarantee funding nor does it risk anything for the city the applications are due november 30th november 30th and we anticipate probably 10 applications this year and we'd like to have each of the organizations attend one of the council meetings or committee meetings between now and november 30th to talk about their projects so that you can as you review the resolutions you can see the projects so you'll see several projects on various agendas in the next couple of months so tonight we have three of them on the agenda since since we struck the last one um each of these well one of these is present tonight and the other two will be present at one of the council meetings in september so i'm not going to talk long about the two that aren't here since you will hear from them later but i can i can talk about them now or wait and do each resolution separately um i think we can do them now okay um so the first resolution is for the lancaster public library it's a it's a million dollar grant request and it is for it's to purchase actually a parking lot close to their book resort project on north marshall street it will provide some income for them as well as a place to continue to have people park so i will let them talk about that they are attending the council meeting next week on september 9th excellent and then i i'm gonna skip here i don't believe anybody from hdc is here i don't see anybody i don't see anyone so theirs is also a request for a million dollars they are working on phase three of the college avenue redevelopment and the phase three is a broader phase that really has some mixed use mixed income space in it so again i will let them talk about that in more detail excellent and then the last one is anchor lancaster and they are actually here this evening so i'm going to wonderful patty to come forward while she's coming there's is also a request for a million dollars um and it is for renovations to the day shelter at tenfold but i'll let her
the explanation good evening thank you for taking the opportunity to hear what i have to say tonight so anchor lancaster is a non-profit that works with the homeless and low income here in lancaster city right now we are our program is housed inside of first united methodist church we've been renting space there for the last nine years we started as just a breakfast program and last year I think we served 42,000 meals to our hungry neighbors we like to listen to what our neighbors have to say and we found out that many of them were taking baths in sinks at market at CVS and we had showers so we started a shower program the goal was to do 12 showers a week last year we did 6,000 showers so yeah um and then during covid we realized that all the public buildings were closed and so we started a day center it just seemed to make sense to us and then we started a laundry program and started a case management program our case management program helped people with um building resumes applying for jobs finding housing helping connect them to medical services drug rehabs and just really meeting them wherever wherever they are we partner with many different other agencies here in the city we work with lancaster general we work with penn state health we work with upmc we work with the social workers at the police station we work with the social workers at tenfold and from the food hub and the outreach worker who works with the merchants here in the city and so our space at the day center it started as just a temporary winter shelter and then we did a temporary summer shelter and we quickly outgrew our space our space was only able to hold less than 20 people and literally it was wall to wall and so we've been searching for another place for our day center and we are just so grateful for tenfold and when they did the temporary shelter last year that one of my caseworkers and i went down and volunteered for the overnight shelter and as i'm standing in that shelter i was just like hmm i wonder if we could be here too so we started a conversation with tenfold and they just have welcomed us with open arms we went for one week we've been there for eight months and we're looking to make more of a permanent partnership with tenfold so we can heat that area cool that area much more efficiently than what it is being done now with that we will need to do some construction of a temporary space but something that we put up a wall and I feel bad saying that we want to put up wall because we're trying to tear walls down with our neighbors but we can put in heating and we can put in cooling and that is our phase one um plan but we're also exploring whether we will move the entire program down to the tenfold space where we would put in a commercial kitchen and if you've been in the garage it's very large and it would be the kitchen the dining room and the day center and then we would there's an annex that is next to it which would be offices it would be our laundry we place for case management to work also would be for bathrooms and showers and that is the request for the funding for
that program thank you so much for that description are there any questions from
committee i just want to thank you for your services for our community i know it's hard i've worked with a board of rescue mission i volunteer and to feed them that's about as far as i go but it's nice to talk to them and see where they're at in life and how they want to improve their life and these services are really important for them to find work and also shelter so thank you so much you're welcome any further questions from the committee
council as a whole thank you council craig just also echoing so much gratitude for the work that anchor does and in particular the willingness to collaborate with other organizations in the city i think is really commendable and it shows you know that we can do a lot to meet a lot of need um and i think what i hear you saying when you're talking about all these things meals showers place to be place to be out of the heat of the cold like you're meeting immediate needs and when we collaborate as as you know all every one of us that's a part of this community if we work together we can do a lot more and so that's one thing that i've admired as i've watched the work that you guys have done and the way that your programming has grown over the years so i just want to really commend you guys best of luck with the application thank you
Thank you. Any further questions from Council as a whole? Or comments?
If I may, Councilor Craig?
Councilor Bites?
First of all, thank you for sharing the outline of the vision, it seems very exciting. Just because we have the mics in front of us, if there's an opportunity for folks to invest their time or treasure into the organization, how can they find out more information?
So they can visit our website at anchorlancaster.org, there is information there about volunteering and about giving.
know it's a passionate subject in our community today so the more that we can help invest our resources into organizations like yours I think it's
worth mentioning thank you thank you can I just add to you I believe the total project is about 1.6 million is that is that correct at least that's what my notes are saying so a little bit more is what I'm saying no it is it's actually
two and a half to three million yes for the day center alone to to put the wall up and lower the ceiling a little bit and put in the unit for heating and cooling is about a hundred and forty thousand thank you are there any
questions or comments from the public
plain 123 south christian why this is a small item on your calendar here but you keep talking about well you don't i mean it always comes up parking throughout lancaster city and i'm always wondering about all the massive parking lots that we have why can't a lot of them be permeable so we don't have all this water running into the source thank you and i think
we'll address that in a little bit okay um can we do these can we do the local shares together or should we do them individually okay thank you so much i'll make a motion to move um the local shares applications administration resolution 61 62 and 63 to full council on the 9th second all those in favor aye thank you council vice that concludes community planning Thank You council Craig I forgot I was
running the meeting today we'll move on to the Public Safety Committee councillor
is yes the public safety committee has administration resolution 59 2025 adopting the lancaster county hazard migration plan and we do have a presentation that will be done by deputy fire chief christopher delong city emergency management coordinator there you go
good evening council good evening mayor this is a culmination of a two-year project that I've been working on with the Lancaster County Emergency Management Agency and fellow municipal leaders in emergency management to update the county hazard mitigation plan. The original plan was written in 2019, and this is the first revision of this plan. The importance of the plan writing and revising is to make sure that We have a current idea of what our hazards are in each municipality in the county. So it's it's a it's a very thorough project usually takes a year took an extra year this time but it goes through and they solicit information from all the municipalities all the public utilities all school districts pretty much everybody that comes in contact with Lancaster County in the municipalities and they try to get a good idea of what the hazards are both natural manmade criminal in certain circumstances. And then this massive plan that's six hundred and seventy four pages gets written and gets presented to each municipality for adoption. And what this does for us it's a written record of our known hazards in our municipalities and then it allows us to submit and apply for grant funding to mitigate those known hazards ahead of time so we can reduce their impacts if they were to occur in our communities. So the team that brought Lancaster City into this project is there's probably at least a dozen of us that have added to the writing of this plan. So me being here is trying to get it adopted. I can give you kind of an idea of what how thorough the plan is but like I said it's 674 pages. It's quite massive but it is very thorough. Most of the hazards and on our side of the plan are public works driven. they are water and wastewater utility projects that we're projecting to address in the next five years so there's no guarantee that we're going to get them accomplished in the next five years but it is a guess that way we can apply for the funding to supplement those projects
thank you so much i do have a question for you would this be with the grants would that be in addition to the FEMA grants as well or is that all combined so there used to be
two FEMA grants that we were eligible for one of the grant one of the grants is no longer active the grant that is still active is the hazard mitigation grant program it's centered around natural hazard resistance which is like earthquakes floods winter storms summer storms that kind of stuff so not exactly what we were hoping for for available grants but we will tell us we will still take advantage of the grants that we are eligible for thank you for that does the
committee have any questions councilor Diaz if I may thank you for the
presentation one question I had is what the county recently ending its partnership with the hazmat environmental fire rescue company does that have any thing to do with this proposal or is that going to affect the plan at all it's a good question so the
plan addresses hazardous materials hazards in the county so this is a little bit more big picture to that whereas that's more um response i think this plan drives the response delivery that any hazardous materials response team would provide coverage to so i don't know if it's completely related certain they're symbiotic in that any response team will take the information identified in this plan and use it to their advantage yes because i did see that they were
planning to work with the neighboring county i just wanted to make sure that the work that we're doing would cover any outside third party that is coming in and absolutely so they're currently
contracting with lebanon county and we actually had an incident since they took over that we've that we worked together on it went very seamless we don't see a difference so far but we're looking forward to the future thank you and that concludes my questions
was that the rotten eggs that was the rotten eggs yes just just so everybody knows there was an incident with the spill of rotten eggs so uh but that was our hazard incident it was nothing more
and very smelly rotten egg it was enough were they rotten before the accident yes yes uh any
other questions from full council then i will go ahead then to move this to full council on september 9th second all in favor aye and the next thing in the agenda is a bill number five 2025 to create a community police review board i believe that you are going to reach out to
chief mendez and i uh to have a discussion um per your comments at the last meeting i haven't
received any response from you or or the chief but you're welcome to bring that forward uh please
feel free to forward me the email request that you sent to chief and i because i didn't receive it
thank you thank you then i will go ahead and hold this until we receive response from the mayor and
chief mendez and and i would just qualify that if i may and until there's a meeting right you had requested a meeting with chief and i okay thank you thank you that would be all for public
works i mean for public safety i believe in mr harris please correct me i believe we need an action to table this yes that would be the best counselor diaz if you would like to make a motion
to table this i'll go ahead and make a motion to table this to the second i guess meeting of city council and so hopefully between now and the next meeting the second meeting will
we'll move forward with that i would suggest tabling it to the to the second meeting of september um that's correct okay is that that's what i was saying uh or the next committee meeting
um yeah just this would be the first time that this is introduced uh so counselor diaz would you like to um i mean this is a bill that you're bringing up through your committee so you can either speak to the bill and address your committee members or you can table it to the next committee meeting in november or i'm sorry excuse me october would you like to make a motion
counselor diaz to motions on the table to then which meeting to the second basically the meeting
the end of september uh and mr harris correct me if i'm wrong but i believe this has to go through committee so the first meeting in november would be the or the committee meeting in november is
when committee well is it september excuse me october i'm skipping a month here all right well that would be the first committee meeting then in october and hopefully i'll get a response
thank you motion is to I would second the motion to table this until the
October meeting of the Public Safety Committee Thank You councillor Diaz we
will now move to the committee of the whole we have three items on the agenda agenda for this evening first is council resolution number 56 2025 which is recognizing welcoming week all councillors receive this resolution and it's celebrating welcoming week from September 12th to September 21st and honoring our neighbors from all around the world who have come to Lancaster and made this their home it also celebrates Lancaster as a certified welcoming city by welcoming america motion to approve you have a motion i have a motion and a second all those in favor aye aye kind of skip comment but i will open it up if council uh would like to have any questions or comments on the resolution or from the public move on to council resolution number 57 recognizing hispanic heritage month this resolution is honoring hispanic heritage month from september 15th to october 15th uh i also note that there is a hispanic heritage month celebration on october 4th in ewell plaza and vince park so if you like to salsa dance i'm sure there's going to be some of that happening in the park uh hispanic heritage month celebration excuse me the city of lancaster is also accepting nominations for the hispanic community achievement award and those applications for nominations are being accepted until september 19th so if you know someone um in the community who has had an impact in the hispanic community here in lancaster i highly encourage you to nominate them with that any questions or comments
from council from the public tony dastra 700 block of new holland avenue um i think this is a good resolution but i do have a request of council for the future um i didn't realize until i'd say a month ago that there was an executive order that determined english is the national language of the united states uh i've long enjoyed the fact that that wasn't the case i think that lancaster needs to consider making spanish an official second language to the city i think there's enough contributions by the hispanic community and spanish speakers that it validates it i mean even the agendas at these meetings are now bilingual which is a great thing I think Lancaster City should Formalize Spanish as an official second language in the government. Thank you. Thank you. Mr. Dastro Any additional public comment? Mr. Vice president, where might people go to nominate their fellow community members? Oh, that's a good question I
Am not sure Mayor Sirachi by chance. Do you know the link on this it is on the city of Lancaster? website city of Lancaster PA go it is slash Hispanic dash heritage dash month Thank You councillor Ahmed awesome with that I will hear a motion to move resolution number 57 to the next full council meeting on September 9th so move we have a motion and a second all those in favor aye third item on the agenda is council resolution number 58 supporting legislation for community solar facilities and I believe that was
brought forward by councillor Hirsch Thank You vice president Arroyo this resolution I'm bringing forward to you all I sent you so awesome information yesterday about what this legislation is in Harrisburg I have a little blurb but I wanted to give a shout out to Elizabeth Hoffman who's a resident who encouraged me to bring this forward endorsing some really good legislation that has passed the Pennsylvania House and is currently sitting in committee in the Pennsylvania State Senate so what I wrote about it is as follows community solar enabling legislation being considered in Harrisburg makes it possible for all Pennsylvania residents to source their electricity from solar many people that would like to install solar panels maybe don't have the space or the proper roof to install them I imagine this is a lot of folks living in Lancaster City who may not have a lot of roof space so the proper roof could then source their electricity from solar with the creation of community energy programs and specifically community solar programs with community solar you can purchase or lease a share of in a community solar project or start a project with your neighbors if you're able to do so every month you receive a credit on your electricity bill for the energy produced by your share Senate bill 504 is the legislation we would endorse with the passage of this resolution this is the enabling legislation that will provide and create a framework for the creation of community energy facilities in Pennsylvania there are currently I think 24 states that have this legislation in place it passed on a bipartisan vote in the Pennsylvania State House by a vote of 114 years to 89 days and was referred to the consumer protection and professional licensure committee in the Pennsylvania State Senate increasing community solar facilities will increase green energy production in Pennsylvania there are 235 proposed community solar facilities that a Penn State study would suggest would add 520 permanent jobs across the Commonwealth and create 800 or sorry eighty three point three million dollars of economic activity in In particular, I personally think about the fact that just a couple miles outside the city, we have farms and other large landowners that could really benefit from something like this, from constructing small-scale solar, which I'll add, is not subject to as much regulatory scrutiny as large-scale solar farms. So there's less kind of hoops that have to be jumped through to make these happen. And I'll add, you know, these would add to the community energy supply, increase grid resilience by decentralizing, creating decentralized sources of energy. The last note I'll add is that this Senate Bill 504 is part of a series of legislation supported by Pennsylvania Governor Shapiro as part of his lightning plan to increase energy production and, in particular, renewable energy production in Pennsylvania. um i'll stop there but i will take any comments from council thank you counselors and if there
are none i will open up to comments from the public elizabeth hoffman 200 block of east ross and thank you very much counselor hirsch for taking this on i'm with a group called third act pennsylvania it's people in their third act of life and we're working on climate change and democracy and this bill is a big focus of our work we're working with a lot of other organizations in like a group called our solar PA and Pennsylvania has been trying to pass this for ten years now this is the eleventh year it's a great way for people who can't afford to put solar on the roof or if their house is too shady or the renters whatever they subscribe to a solar project so they're not actually owning it leasing it or anything they're just subscribing it and I did have this in Maryland and it's you know you don't notice it on your bill there's consolidated billing so you just select that you want to subscribe to a project and you get a credit and you're putting solar electrons on the grid so Pennsylvania is 49th it ranks 49th in the growth of renewable energy so we're really falling behind we only we get less than 1% of our energy from solar so we think this is an easy way to add solar to the grid and thank you again for considering it are there any other comments from the
public why people can't do this already I mean like what about this bill makes this it people able to do it doesn't you know like why why do we need this bill so that people can do this is it federal federally not allowed state not allowed
yeah I think we should do this and I'll just I was just gonna quickly add just from the research that I had been doing a lot of it is just about setting up a like I mean I hate to use the word framework because that sounds very I don't know I don't know what the other word would be but just kind of like like creating a system to expedite the process of creating community solar yeah it's correct yes are there any other comments from the public I'll just echo what miss Hoffman just said is we're their organization is trying to get as many municipalities to support this as possible to you know kind of create positive momentum to get the Senate to pass this Thank You councillor hers for
bringing this forward do I hear a motion to move resolution number 58 to full council motion so moved I'll second we have a motion and second all those in favor aye that concludes our agenda for this evening final item for tonight is the clerk's report and I believe mr. Harris submitted that in writing are you okay if we skip the verbal report yes thank you mr. Harris with that I'll hear motion to adjourn the committee meeting motion to adjourn second all those in favor aye